Dr. M. Usman Maqbool **Bhutta**

POSTDOCTORAL FELLOW · DEPARTMENT OF MECHANICAL AND AUTOMATION ENGINEERING, CUHK, HK

Room 205, Academic Building 1, CUHK, Hong Kong.

□ (+852) 609-44-786 | wsmanmaqbool@outlook.com | # usmanmaqbool.github.io | □ UsmanMaqbool | □ usmanmaqbool

"Roboticist + Entrepreneur"

Summary.

With the rise of autonomous systems, being a researcher and entrepreneur, my research direction is their deployment to the real world. For any autonomous mode of the robot, a 3D map is essential to navigate and operate at any place. I work to tackle the problems related to scale difference and loop closures for large scale 3D mapping. I've 7+ years of experience specializing in robotics R&D and project management. I previously owned an IT company, and I've been part of several startups since 2011. My full profile can view here (https://usmanmaqbool.github.io/).

Work Experience

Research (Computer Vision Technologies and Robotics System)

C3 Robotics Laboratory (C3RL), Department of Mechanical and Automation Engineering

CUHK, Hong Kong.

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

May. 2021 - Present

- Supervisor: Prof. Darwin Lau, Director of C3 Robotics Laboratory (C3RL), The Chinese University of Hong Kong CUHK, Hong Kong...
- Research in place recognition, AR/VR and inspection robotics for construction I'm working on several projects here

Place Recognition: Working on the light-weight representation of images and making better use of previously trained models.

AR/VR: Research in **AR/VR** Platform design, multi-agent mixed reality, assistive prosthetics for the handicapped persons, teleoperated robots, human-robot interaction.

Inspection: Deep learning based research for the robotic presurface inspection for the construction.

Multi-agent collaboration: For indoor vegetation and painting robotics application.

Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, Robotics Institute

HKUST, HK

PhD

Sep 2016 - Feb 2021

- PhD Supervisor: Prof Ming Liu, Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (RAM-LAB)
- Research Contributions as First Author

Place Recognition: Our work makes a leap towards hierarchical deep learning-based place recognition for multiagent SLAM systems. We introduce a probabilistic layer to constrain the local representation along with the global representation of images. The global description of the pre-trained model and the local consistency introduced in our work enables the system to yield good performance at large-scale.

Development Using: MATLAB, Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, Docker, Deep learning, Matconvnet

Multi-Agent SLAM: I've produced Loop-box for the multi-Agent Direct SLAM Triggered by Single Loop Closure for Large scale semi dense 3D reconstruction /large-scale structure from motion. This work is accepted for publication in IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics (IF= 11+)..

Development using: C++ 11, ROS, OpenCV, OpenGV, Paraview, EVO, UGV, LSD-SLAM, Monocular Camera.

SLAM: I've worked mainly for the multi-agent SLAM system. To find the scale difference and excellent relative transformation between difference agents. I've produced PCR-Pro work. This work got best student paper finalist award at IEEE-CYBER 2018.

Development using: C++ 11, ROS, OpenCV, OpenGV, Paraview, EVO, Monocular Camera, Plotly

Automation (Inspection): For smartphone glass inspection, I've introduced Smart-Inspect work. This work is accepted in IROS 2020. The patent is also under-review in the US.

Development using: Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, K-Means, Docker, Machine learning (ML)

Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL)

ETH Zürich, Switzerland.

Academic Guest

MPhil Candidate

Oct. 2019 - Mar. 2020

- Supervisor: Prof. Roland Siegwart, Director of Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL), ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Co-Supervisor: Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma, Senior Researcher at ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Research in Place Recognition: I've worked for making the better place recognition for the better scene understanding. Furthermore, I've also introduced light weight representation of key-frames for better channel utilization.

Development using: MATLAB, Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, Docker, Deep learning, Matconvnet

Department of Electronics

OAU, Pakistan

• M.Phil. Supervisor: **Prof Hasan Mahmood**, Department of Electronics, QAU.

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

• Research in Image Processing (CNN): I've introduced CNN-based license plate recognition of Pakistani's Cars. This work has been published in IEEE-ICALIP 2014.

Industry and Entrepreneurship

Lisee Technology Corporation Limited

00 Jan 2018 - Jan 2021

- Won funding support for company | TSSSU Support HK\$ 300,000 (Jun 19 - May 20).

- Indoor Navigation for Libray using Lisee Technology | PCF Support HK\$ 160,000 (Jun 18 - May 19).

Friends Corporate Technologies

Islamabad, PK

Central HK

CEO Feb 2013 - Aug 2015

50+ Projects | Electronics/ Electrical Engineering, R&D, image processing, Web Applications Development, MVC Applications

Federal Government of Pakistan

Islamabad, PK

Scientific Officer

May 2012 - Feb 2013

Electronics/ Electrical Engineering, R&D, image processing

Server4Sale, LLC Islamabad, PK

PHP Developer Dec 2009 - Mar 2010

Php web application development for Joomla and Zend frameworks.

Academic

Department of Computer Science BZU-Sahiwal, Pakistan

Lecturer (Visiting)

Feb 2016 - Jun 2016

Teaching MCS and BS-CS courses

Department of Physics GPGC Sahiwal, Pakistan

CTI Oct. 2015 - May. 2016

Teaching BS physics (Electronics related courses + Labs + Projects)

Department of Electronics QAU, Pakistan

Instructer

Aug. 2010 - Dec. 2010

'PHP Web Development' (a short course) offered in Department of Electronics, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.

Education

Ph.D. in Robotics and AI at RAM-LAB, Robotics Institute

HKUST, Hong Kong

Department of Electronic & Computer Engineering, The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology

Sep. 2016 - Feb. 2021

Thesis: "Towards A Swift Multiagent SLAM System For Large-scale Robotics Applications", June 17, 2021

• PhD Supervisor: Prof Ming Liu, Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (RAM-LAB)

- Exchange Supervisor: Prof. Roland Siegwart, Director of Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL), ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Exchange Co-Supervisor: Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma, Senior Researcher at ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Got PEEF CCMS PhD scholarship from Pakistan and overseas research award (ORA).
- Research: Multi-Agent SLAM System, Place Recognition, Autonomous Car and Deep Learning for automation industry. Hand on experience on RGB-D 3D recontruction, Multi-view stereo, python and C++ development experience, multi-threaded coding.3D mesh registration, paraview and parameterizations. Moreover, I've deep understanding of data structures and algorithms. Experience with software development on Linux open-source stack. Calculus, linear algebra and geometry related courses have been taken.

M.Phil. in Electronics QAU, Pakistan

Department of Electronics, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

- M.Phil. Supervisor: **Prof Hasan Mahmood**, Department of Electronics, QAU.
- Research: Signal and Image Processing
- Grade: A

M.Sc. in Electronics QAU, Pakistan

Department of Electronics, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

• 2nd position in batch

· Projects: completed 9+ projects related to C++, Verilog/HDL and Micro-controller programming.

B.Sc. in Mathematics and Physics

BZU, Pakistan

Bahauddin Zakariya University, Multan Pakistan

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

• Grade: 1st Division

Presentation

Posters Presentation Jul. 2021

• 'Mixed Reality in Hands-On Learning of Robotics' by Xinyan Zhao, Sabrina Lam, M. Usman M. Bhutta, Darwin Lau and Jimmy Lee.

 'Online Robotics Laboratory Framework for Interactive and Group Hands-On Learning' by Ken Hui, Ken Kwok, M. Usman M. Bhutta, Darwin Lau and Jimmy Lee.

IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems [IROS, 2020]

Las Vegas, USA

Presentor as author

Presentor as author

Oct. 2020

• Introduced Smart-Inspect for the micro scale localization and classification of smartphone glass defects for industrial automation.

Technology Start-up Support Scheme for Universities (TSSSU)

HKUST, Hong Kong

Presenter as COO Lisee Technology Corporation Company Limited, Hong Kong.

Jan. 2019

• Introduced Lisee technology in front of selection committee panel and won TSSSU 2019-20 funding of the amount of HK\$300,000.

IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Intelligent Systems [IEEE-CYBER 2018]

Tianjin, China

Introduced PCR-Pro for the estimation of information matrix and scale difference for pose graph SLAM.

IET-Young Professionals Exhibition and Competition (IET-YPEC) 2018

CityU, Hong Kong

Presenter as COO Lisee Technology Corporation Company Limited, Hong Kong.

Jul. 2018

Jul. 2018

• Introduced Lisee technology at IET-YPEC 2018.

Campus Challenge @ HKUST Transportation

HKUST, Hong Kong

Presenter as participent

May 2018

Dec. 2017

3

HKUST got 80+ proposals for this compeitions, and arranged a roadshow. My proposal got selected for the audiance award after getting maximum votes.

High Tech Innovation and Entrepreneurship

HKUST, Hong Kong

Presenter as Entrepreneur

· Introduced my study related to the flying cars.

World First Youth Robotics Developemnt Forum 2017

Shangri-La Shenzhen, China.

Presenter as author.

Nov. 2017

• Introduced my work related to multi-agent SLAM system.

Honors & Awards

July, 2021 Educational Technology Innovation: Gold Award, The Teaching and Learning Innovation Expo, CUHK CUHK, Hong Kong July, 2021 Pedagogical Innovation: Silver Award, The Teaching and Learning Innovation Expo, CUHK CUHK, Hong Kong Best Student Paper Finalist Award, IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Julv. 2018 Tianjin, China Intelligent Systems May, 2018 Audience Award, Campus Challenge - Transportation, HKUST HKUST, HK Nov, 2017 Best Mapper Award, Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, HKUST Shenzhen, China May, 2017 Completion Award, The Graduate Teaching Assistant Training, HKUST HKUST, HK Dec, 2016 Best External Award, Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, HKUST Shenzhen, China Nov, 2016 Completion Award, Author Workshop, Elsevier Publishing Campus HKUST, HK CCMS PhD Scholarship, Won Chief Minister Marit Scholarship (CCMS) scholarship award by Punjab Lahore, PK Government (PEEF), Pakistan for pursuing my PhD studies at HKUST, HK Sep 2013 Participant, Painting for peace (Pakistan-India-Afghanistan) event, a part of the Harmony initiative Islamabad, PK Apr 2013 Participant, Case Spark in business plan competition Islamabad, PK Apr 2013 Participant, Case EPICA Islamabad, PK Apr 2013 Participant, How to be a Better Playwright Workshop by PNCA and US Embassay Pakistan Islamabad, PK Oct 2012 Participant, Punjab Youth Festival Lahore, PK Oct 2011 Participant, Int'l Youth Conference and Festival Islamabad, PK Sep 2011 Participant, Asian Youth Conference and Peace Festival Lahore, PK Apr 2011 Completion Award, Acting and Directing Theater Workshop by PNCA and US Embassay Pakistan Islamabad, PK Dec 2011 Participant, National Drama Festival Islamabad, PK Dec 2010 Instuctor of short Course, PHP Web Development' at the Department of Electronics, QAU Islamabad, PK Apr 2013 Completion Award, Running River Rafting course by Adventure Foundation of Pakistan Mansehra, PK Apr 2013 Completion Award, Paragliding course by QAU Adventure Club Islamabad, PK Dec 2008 Award of Honor, Finance Secretary of Electronics Student Society (ESS) at QAU Islamabad, PK

Academic Activities

RA-L	Referee Service, IEEE Robotics and Automation Letter	2022
TC	Referee Service, IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics	2020, -21
ICRA	Referee Service, IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Robotics and Automation	2022, -21, -20
IROS	Referee Service, IEEE/RSJ RA-L and International Conference on Robotics and Automation	2021,-20, -19, -18
HKUST, HK Teaching Assistant , EESM 5547 - Multimedia Signal Processing		Spr 2020, Spr 2019,
		Spr 2018
CASE	Referee Service, IEEE International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering	2019
HKUST, HK Teaching Assistant , ELEC4820 - Medical Imaging		Fall 2018
HKUST, HK Teaching Assistant , ELEC 1010 - Electronic and Information Technology		Spr 2017

Skills

Robotics and Computer Vision Ubuntu, ROS, PCL, Docker, Catkin, OpenCV, OpenGV, Ceres Solver, g2o, Libpointmatcher

Machine Learning / Deep Learning Jupyter, Pytorch, Tensorflow, Keras, CUDA

Programming Python, C/C++, Matlab, git, LaTeX, FPGA, Verilog

Web mkdocs, Hugo, Jekyll, PHP, MYSQL

Languages English, Urdu

Research Publication

Robust mobile robot navigation in cluttered environments based on hybrid adaptive Journal (IF: 8.8+) neuro-fuzzy inference and sensor fusion

Muhammad Husnain Haider, Zhonglai Wanga, Abdullah Aman Khan, Hub Ali, Hao Zheng, Aug 2022 Shaban Usman, Rajesh Kumar, M. Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Pengpeng Zhi

2022 Journal of King Saud University-Computer and Information Sciences.

MAFNet: Segmentation of Road Potholes with Multi-modal Attention Fusion Network for **Autonomous Vehicles**

Zhen Feng, Yanning Guo, Qing Liang, M. Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Hengli Wang, Ming Liu, and Aug 2022 **Yuxiang Sun**

2022 IEEE Transactions on Instrumentation & Measurement

Autonomous Mobile Robot Navigation using Adaptive Neuro Fuzzy Inference System

Muhammad Husnain Haider and Hub Ali and Abdullah Aman Khan and Hao Zheng and M.

Usman Maqbool Bhutta and Shaban Usman and Pengpeng Zhi and Zhonglai Wang

2022 International Conference On Innovations And Development Of Information Technologies And Robotics (IDITR), 2022

Why-So-Deep: Towards Boosting Previously Trained Models for Visual Place Recognition

M Usman Maqbool Bhutta*, Yuxiang Sun, Darwin Lau and Ming Liu

IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L)/ICRA, 2022

Scale-Adaptive Pothole Detection and Tracking from 3-D Road Point Clouds

Wu, Rigen and Fan, Jiahe and Guo, Libo and Qiao, Lei and Bhutta, M. Usman Maqbool and Hosking, Brett and Vityazev, Sergey and Fan, Rui

2021 IEEE International Conference on Imaging Systems and Techniques (IST), 2021

Loop-box: Multi-Agent Direct SLAM Triggered by Single Loop Closure for Large Scale Mapping

M Usman Magbool Bhutta*, Manohar Kuse, Rui Fan, Yanan Liu and Ming Liu 2022 IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics

Smart-Inspect: Micro Scale Localization and Classification of Smart Phone Glass Defects for Industrial Automation

M Usman Maqbool Bhutta*, Shoaib Aslam, Peng Yun, Jianhao JIAO and Ming Liu IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS 2020)

Multiple Lane Detection Algorithm Based on Optimised Dense Disparity Map Estimation

Han Ma, Yixin Ma, Jianhao Jiao, M Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Mohammud Junaid Bocus, Lujia Wang, Ming Liu and Rui Fan

Accepted in IEEE International Conference on Imaging Systems and Techniques (IST 2018)

Journal (**IF: 5.3+**)

Conference Paper

May 2022

Journal (IF: 5.4+)

Jan 2022

Conference Paper

Aug 2021

Journal (IF: 11.7+)

Oct 2020

Conference Paper

Oct 2020

Conference Paper

Dec 2018

PCR-Pro: 3D Sparse and Different Scale Point Clouds Registration and Robust Estimation of Information Matrix For Pose Graph SLAM

Conference Paper

M Usman Magbool Bhutta* and Ming Liu

Jul 2018

Presented in IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Intelligent Systems (IEEE-CYBER 2018), and won Best Student Paper Finalist Award.

An intelligent approach for robust detection and recognition of multiple color and font styles automobiles license plates: A feature-based algorithm

Conference Paper

M Usman Maqbool Bhutta*, Hasan Mahmood, and Haroon Malik

Jan 2015

Published in IEEE International Conference on Audio, Language and Image Processing (ICALIP 2014).

Efficient Reset Design Techniques

Journal Paper

Qamar, Zoha, Bushra Yaseen, and Usman Magbool

2015

Published in Science International Lahore

Patent

Semi-Supervised Learning Approach for Smart Phone Glasses Defect Inspection

US Patent

Muhammad Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Jianhao Jiao, Peng Yun, Yuan Wang, Xuebin Sun, Ming Liu

Jan 2020

U.S. Provisional Patent Application No. 62/974,937, Filing Date 01/06/2020.

Automatic Surface Defect Detection System for Smart Phone Glass Based on Deep Learning

US Patent

Yuan Wang, Jianhao Jiao, Peng Yun, Muhammad Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Xuebin Sun, Ming Liu U.S. Provisional Patent Application No. 62/974,938, Filing Date 01/06/2020.

Jan 2020

References

Prof Darwin Lau

Postdoc Supervisor Associate Professor · Director of C3 Robotics Lab (C3RL), Department of Mechanical and darwinlau@cuhk.edu.hk

Automation Engineering, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, HK. (+852) 3943 8523

Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma

Exchange Co-Supervisor

Senior Researcher · ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland

(+41) (0) 44 633-8803

cesarcadena.lerma@gmail.com

Prof Ming Liu

Associate Professor · Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (RAM-LAB), Department

of Electronic and Computer Enginneering, HKUST, HK.

(+852) 2358 7058

Ph.D. Supervisor

eelium@ust.hk

5